Hello! In this video you will learn how to escape a privilegeddocker container.
Before I understood how docker containes work. I thought that they are insanely complicated. They are surely not easy, but they are also
not that hard. This video will give you an idea about it.
This episode based on a blogpost by Disconnect3d
from Trail of Bits. He's also my friend and he hugely helped my to start by cybersecurity career,
so make sure to give him a follow! Links, as always, are in the description. Enjoy!
Docker containers are somewhat similar to virtual machines - each one is better for different use-cases. The difference is, among others,
that VMs virtualise the hardware and have separate kernel.
Containers, on the other hand, are much ligher. On the lower level, they are just processes isolated from the rest of the system.
It has many benefits when you want to create an application.
For example, container will be much lighter than the VM and much easier
to deploy. However, from the security point of
view, it is more risky because there's less isolation between the container and the host operating system.
It is possible to configure your container securely.
Then, even if you would have an RCE in the webapp
that's inside the container, the attacker wouldn't be able to escalate his privileges
to the host machine. However, creating a secure container is not trivial.
Often, the easiest way to solve some problem is by giving the
container additional privileges.
In today's episode you see how easy it is to escape a container
that has too much permissions.
Keep in mind, I am not showing you a docker vulnerability that only works in outdated versions.
It's a repeatable way to escape the container with specific privileges in the newest version of docker.
Precisely, we need to run in the container as root user
and we need the ability to use the mount command.
Let's start by explaining control groups or just cgroups
It's a Linux feature
that allows grouping processes and limiting resources like CPU time
of those groups. It's also one of mechanisms
with which docker isolates processes inside the container from those of the host.
And there's a feature that allows to execute a specific command once
all processes in the cgroup are terminated.
For example, this can be used to notify the kernel
that all processes in the cgroup are terminated
and the group can be removed.
This is the feature that will be exploited to escape the container, because this command will be executed on the host.
Let's jump to the exploit and explain it step by step.
So we start an ubuntu container. These are the insecure options that will allow us to use the mount command.
--cap-add is for adding capabilities. Now what are capabilities?
Before them, each process would be either non-privileged, subject to all permission checks, or privileged -
efectively run as root, bypassing all kernel permission checks. Capabilities divide those privileges
and allow more granular granting. For example, CHOWN capability allows changing file's owner
while KILL capability allows sending any signals. SYS_ADMIN is a very powerful capability
which will give us the ability to use the mount syscall. Deciding on granting or restricting
each capability upon creation of a new container would be very time-consuming. This problem is
partially solved by AppArmor. Among other things, AppArmor can specify a list of restricted capabilities.
This command turns off docker-default AppArmor profile, because it restricts
the SYS_ADMIN capability which we need.
Running this command gives us a shell inside the container
and our goal is to execute a command on the host.
The first step of the exploit is creating a new cgroup and, using mount command, telling de system
where are the files that describe this cgroup.
Because in practice, cgroup is just a bunch of files and this is its structure.
There's one file particularly interesting to us - notify_on_release.
When the value inside this file is 0
nothing happens when all processes from the cgroup are terminated.
However, when the value is 1, upon terminating all processes, a command from release_agent file from upper directory is executed.
So in our exploit, we put the value 1 inside notify_on_release file in our cgroup.
The command that we will want to execute will be put inthe /cmd file inside the container.
If our attack will be successful, this file will be executed by the host.
However, if we run /cmd on the host, there will be "No such file" error, because the host won't know that this file is inside the container.
And obviously, being in the container we can't just write a file on the host OS.
So we need to find under what path files from inside the container are reachable on the host.
For this, we need to look in the /etc/mtab file. And we'll use a handy regex to extract this path.
Next, we put this path inside the release_agent file.
Then, we put our command that will be executed on the host inside this /cmd file.
In this case, we'll just list processes of the host and put the result inside the /output file inside the container so we can read it later.
So for this whole thing to be triggered, all processes from the cgroup must be terminated.
But there are no processes in the cgroup yet.
To add process to the cgroup, we need to put this process' id inside the cgroup.procs file.
So we create a new process and all it does is putting its PID inside this cgroup.procs file.
$$ is a special bash variable that contains each process' own id.
And that process is terminated just after doing that. And that's the moment when the release_agent is executed.
And in this case, the release_agent is out /cmd file.
So on the host the ps command is executed and the result is put inside the /output file inside the container.
We can then cat this file and see the result which proves that the attack was successful and we were able to escape the container.
To prevent such attack from happening, when creating a docker container, always remember
to avoid using --privileged flag, because is basically gives the container full access to the host.
Also, never mount docker socket inside the container, because then, the attacker would be able
to create a new privileged container himself and use this technique.
And also, never run as root inside the container, because it opens a lot of potential attack vectors to escalate privileges.
Because keep in mind that the root inside the container is not some different root.
By default, its exactly the same user as root on the host.
I hope that after watching the video, you understand container escapes a little bit better.
If you do, support the channel by leaving a like or maybe even buying me a coffe.
Also, sign up for my mailing list to not miss any of my videos or other products.
Anyway, for now thanks for watching and goodbye!